Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hey, heat.
Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome back to the Ask Abijit show.
I hope everybody is doing great.
Everyone's doing fantastic. Let us see
who all is there on the live stream.
Before we get into the questions, before
we dive in, I can see Rishi Patel, Mr.
haters, Shagun, Chopra, Arian, Rocking
Gaming, Baratia Edits, Tanay, Chandra,
Illuminati Creek, Anand Chandak, Ankit,
Vashish, Real Eyes, Meit Bat, Surange,
Kapil, Rashmi, Ratour, Vidi, Manyar,
Abhishek, Paleria, Ashish Singh, Shri
Ramachandra, Namaha, Surendra Gupta,
Alvin, Rodriguez, Shravani, Pranay, Paul
from Kolkata, Shilaja, Vami, Vamshi,
Kalem, Akshit, Lavish, Sharma, Lavish,
Sharma Om Gupta Hirkumar Patel Nishal Ry
Feminist Hunter Abhishek Hila Pratam
Agarwal Red Rangers Wolf Rashmi Ratur
Geopolitical Dubai Anant Chandak Laksh
Deep Bhak Krishna Govinda Alfred Gunat
Bulvay Savia Set uh Ka Red uh who else
do we have? We have Gulu. We have unique
pixels. We have Samarati, Somi, Jane,
Ram, Krishna, Param, Hans, uh, Diddi
Dudu, Baller Attitude, Shre Shreas,
Mishra, Xenom, Morphosis, Hirk, Kumar,
Patel, Pakar, Gupta, D, Dib, Tanu,
Sarcar, Geopolitical, Dubai from Indor,
Meit Bat, Surenda Gupta, Fate, Anand
Sutram, Re Skywalker, Viral, Viral,
Viral,
Patel, Rajat, Duhan and so many other
people. Abhijit supreme lord is there.
Abhishek pande is there. Dyam Chawan who
wants to talk about tariffs and so much
more. All right. All right. Good to see
you all and thank you so much for being
on this live chat. Now let's get into
the questions. We have questions. Lots
of questions. A lot happening in the
world. The whole world is being shaken
up by things. Yeah. Lots of stuff. So
let's discuss what's happening. Let's
take questions from a variety of
uh themes. Yeah. So let's see what do we
have. Uh let's begin with this question.
What is this question is from Argentina
Paro. I have heard that Hinduism isn't a
religion. It is beyond religion. It's a
philosophy of life. So what is religion?
What's the deal? It's a good question
and yeah people say that Hinduism isn't
a religion. It's a way of life. So
what's the real real deal? What's what
is Hinduism? What it is? What is it
actually?
So clearly Hinduism isn't see when when
we talk about a religion the word or
term religion we look at it or define it
mentally subconsciously unconsciously
from an Abrahamic
perspective let me tell you a story so
more than 20 years ago more than 20
years ago long time ago I was in a
casino in Atlantic City New Jersey that
Trump that casino was called the Trump
Taj Mahal it no longer exists. I believe
it it closed down. And don't ask me how
I ended up there. It's because of uh the
people I was with, you
know, young Indian cyber coolies who
wanted to get a taste of America. So I
also was with them and that's how I
ended up in a casino in Atlantic City.
So I'm in this uh in in this casino, the
Trump Taj Mahal at and at some point in
time I end up I I find myself next to a
guy who seems to be of Mexican origin.
He seems to be a descendant of the
Aztecs, the Trip Triple Alliance. Uh,
and uh, he's very drunk and he he's
trying to be to be friendly. He's trying
to make friends with me. So, he's asking
me what what what's your religion? What
what god do you worship? What what book
do you read? So, I said I I read lots of
books. He said, "No, no, what is the
book? Is it is it the Bible? Is it is it
Quran?" I said, "I have I have lots of
books. I I couldn't really answer his
question." So then he's asking me okay
forget about books. What what god do you
worship? So I said have you heard of
Shiva? He says what is Shiva? I said
have you heard of Krishna? He says no no
no. I I said I have lots of gods. He
said no no one god. One god. Do you
worship Jesus? Do you worship Buddha? Uh
do do you worship what? Allah. So I said
have you heard of Buddha? He says yes
I've heard of Buddha. Oh yeah yeah yeah
I now get it. I I get it now. So
according to these people, so so I could
not give any name of Hindu gods because
the guy didn't understand it. But if I
said Buddha, he got it. He kind of got
it. He kind of got it. Yeah. So from
these people's perspective, religion is
about one book, one God and one prophet.
And Hinduism is not a religion from this
perspective, from this definition.
Hinduism is not uh ideological. It's not
dogmatic. It is not um it is not a
militaristic top- down structure
politically organized uh religion as
such. Hinduism is more philosophical
than ideological or dogmatic. I mean
there's no ideology or dogma in in
Hinduism. And it's got a whole bunch of
lots of different philosophical schools
of thought. And these schools of thought
can be divided into the Astic and the
Nastic schools of thought. Okay. The
astic schools of thought are the other
schools of thought that uh accept the
authority of the Vedas and the Nastik
schools of thought do not accept the
authority of the Vedas. And today nobody
really follows any of this but
historically that's how it was. So you
know the Astic schools of thought were
called vimmansa, virant, sananka, yoga,
nyaya and vehashik. These are the
schools of thought. Some of these
believe in the existence of the soul and
and the existence of God. And some of
these don't believe in the existence of
God but they believe in the existence of
the soul. And then you have the gnostic
schools of thought which do not
recognize the authority of the Vedas
like Charvaka which is pure materialism
completely atheistic. Then you have
bodha and then you have ja. So these are
various schools of thought within the
dharmic umbrella. Um and this includes
jarvaka which is pure atheism, pure
materialism. So you can see how diverse
Hinduism is. Uh Hindu Dharma is. So it's
it's not monolithic at all. It's
extraordinarily diverse. You can have
wildly differing interpretations of the
world. All these schools of thought are
essentially models of the universe.
These are essentially philosophical
models of the universe which have an
inherent inbuilt logic within them and
so on. So it's it's very different from
uh the various
uh Abrahamic religions extremely
different from those and you will find
that despite having such incredible wide
ranging variety in in the worldview in
these schools of thought they all have
the same moral values uh and the same
ethics. So the the both the ethics, the
Janna ethics, the Charvaka ethics, the
sananka ethics, the vidanta ethics, they
essentially the same. There's no
difference in those things. But the
interpretations of whether there is God
or not, whether the soul exists or not
and various other things, that's wildly
different. So it's a very diverse thing.
Everything is allowed in Hinduism. You
can be an atheist and you can be a
Hindu. You can believe in 78 million
gods if you if you wish to and you can
be a Hindu. You can worship your
ancestors and their spirits if you want
to be a Hindu. You can worship the
spirits of the of the forests and the
trees if you want to be and you can
still be a Hindu or you can just worship
one god if you like and that is also
part of Hinduism. So it's extremely
plural, it's extremely diverse, it's uh
it's a philosophy of life you could say.
There's no real definition of Hinduism
but it's way broader than the uh much
narrower definition that you uh see
within the Abrahamic uh religions. So
Hinduism is way way way broader than
that. It's very inclusive,
extraordinarily inclusive. And if you
see the history of India, you'll say
that everyone was welcome, welcomed. Uh
yeah, extremely inclusive, extremely
welcoming, extremely respectful, not
just merely tolerant and so on. So yeah,
that in brief is what you call
Hinduism. Okay, Aayush says and Aayush
has been asking this for a very long
time. So I thought let me take this up.
So let let's see the question is can you
show some historical evidences recipes
etc that people in India used to have a
non-vegetarian diet in the past my
friends and relatives don't believe me
maybe they'll believe after watching you
okay so uh let me show you a plethora of
of of different pieces of evidence yeah
let's do that uh let's
uh for a change we'll not go to the map
we'll go to our friend
Google so Google and let's uh Google
something. Okay, let's say Ganga Valley
[Music]
harpoons.
Harpoons. So, copper horde culture
second millennium BC and so on. You get
all these harpoons, you know, that that
that were used for fishing and and
spearing various fish and all that. So,
and you can also use this for warfare,
but you can see from the way it is
constructed, it's it's uh designed for,
you know, trapping fish for for ensuring
that uh the fish don't escape once you
they are speared with this. You can also
use this in warfare. So, that's one
piece of circumstantial evidence that
I'm offering you. But maybe you will
say, "No, no, no. It was used for
warfare. It was not used for killing
fish or animals." Yeah. Okay. So, let us
then Google something else. Okay. Let's
go back to our friend Google and let me
Google
this. I'm going to Google a very
specific term here. It is called
manasolasa. So what was manasolasa?
Let's go to Wikipedia briefly and please
remember Wikipedia is not a reliable
source of information. I'm just doing it
taking a look for the sake of brevity.
So manas also known as this is an early
12th century Sanskrit text composed by
the kalyani chaluka king sowara III who
ruled in present day Karnataka. So he
ruled in Karnataka in the 12th century
you know 1100s you know around that time
and he wrote this uh text in Sanskrit uh
while he was ruling. It's an
encyclopedic work covering topics such
as polity, governance, ethics,
economics, astronomy, astrology,
rhetoric, veterinary, medicine,
horiculture, perfumes, food,
agriculture, games, dancing, poetry, and
music. It also includes food by the way
and so on so forth. And what do we get
in it? It's got a whole structure to it,
governance and all. And what kind of
food do we get? So, it contains recipes
of vegetarian and non-vegetarian
cuisines. Among the meat dishes, the
text does not include the meat of cow,
horse, elephant, parrot, peacock or
eggs. It describes cuisines based on
pork, venison, which is deer meat and
goat meat and fish among others. Now,
like I said, you can't really trust
Wikipedia. Wikipedia is known to be
super biased against us, especially when
it comes to India. So, now let's go and
actually open one of these. Let's let's
go for one of PDF and let's open one of
these. For example, this one. Let's open
this one.
Yeah. And let's try and take a look at
what the actual translation. So this is
uh okay. Maharaja Gakar of Boda he uh
commissioned this translation back in
the day 1939. So this should be a little
more significantly more uh reliable. So
let's go around somewhere around page
20. What do we have? Anabog
uh vegetarian meal etc and so on. Hingu
water means hing. That's fine. All
right. That's all right. If doas at
least while describing non-vegetarian
preparations, the method of removing the
hair of a pig is given. Haha. And yeah,
it tells you how the hair of a pig
should be should be removed. And uh in
the opinion of the author, dishes
prepared in earn vessels taste well.
Peculiar mice living in the fields near
rivers are also included in the non in
the non-vegetarian food. So I think here
we have significantly more
reliable actually unquestionable
evidence of uh meat being eaten in
ancient India. I don't think I don't
understand why people are so skeptical
when you tell them that Indians used to
eat meat. Indians always ate meat. It's
not like you know you can't project
today's lifestyle back into the old
days. Back in the day some people ate
meat. Today some people eat meat and
back in the day thousands of years ago
some people did not eat meat and same
the same applies today right for example
you have more over here for instance
describing two methods of attracting
forest deer
um one second uh this is what what is
this about user deer right deer hunting
kind of hunting in which the deer are
killed when they come into the forest
and so on so yeah there's deer hunting
over here Right? And when at the
appointed place the hunters bring the
decoing deer along with the forest deer,
the latter are killed by the king with
arrows. There you have it. So listen,
let's not be let's not be naive. Let's
not be
childish,
okay? We we are the the inheritors of a
very ancient, very pluralistic uh
heritage and we have had all kinds of
lifestyles within India. Some people ate
meat, some people hunted, some people
were pure vegetarian. Everything was
allowed. So let's not try and
superimpose some monolithic idealistic
worldview on on the past. So I I hope
what I showed is clear evidence of the
fact that Indians used to eat non-veg
meat in the past, especially warriors,
especially kings for sure. And there was
no controversy back in the day like we
have today. All kinds of people fighting
each other constantly over tiny little
minor
matters. What language should be spoken
and what what food should be eaten and
so on. Come on, everything's okay. Some
things aren't allowed like you know
never in in Indian history you will find
in any text the uh certain animals being
eaten for example you know what I mean
and so
on. Okay. Amisha says where did India's
people come from? Who who are Indians
genetically closest to? How did humans
survive the ice age? I'm glad someone
asked these questions. It reminds me of
something I wrote a long time ago. So,
let's once again go to our friend
Google. And let's see. Arian invasion
myth. And when I search for that, what
do I get? I get this article from Medium
that I wrote. Let's open this article.
This is an article I wrote. It's in
medium and I don't need this right now.
And you can see I wrote this on May
14th, 2017. That's a long time ago now.
And this is the article from which
everybody gets their knowledge initial
knowledge of the RN invasion theory.
Today you have so many
scholars who are all fighting the good
good fight that the RN invasion theory
is false. But this is the article that
started everything. This is the one
article in which all the evidence is
presented in one place. This is what
started everything. This is the article
and today everybody has taken this
forward. Now anyhow uh let's uh let's
look at this in in the concluding par
concluding section conclusion before the
references here we have this this
paragraph that I wrote in 2017. Who were
the first Indians? When did they first
arrive in India? Where from? What were
their lives like? What was their society
like? What did how did ancient Indian
civilization evolve? What knowledge did
they possess? What kind of science did
they have? What discoveries did they
make? What technologies did they
develop? How did they build the largest
ancient urban civilization the world has
ever seen? What did they call their
great cities? What language did they
speak? Did they really develop a
protodemocracy thousands of years before
the Greeks? What kind of future did they
envisage for India? What lessons can we
learn from them? These are the questions
our eminent historians have not dained
to ask for the past seven decades and
these are the questions we must seek in
order to rediscover our roots and
understand who we really are. So yeah,
so that's what I wrote a long time ago
and I'm glad people are asking this. I'm
glad asked this. So the question is
where did the people of India come from?
Great
question and for that we have to go back
about 70,000 80 75,000 maybe 80,000
years before today and it all starts
okay now we go to the map okay we
haven't cracked down the map we'll crack
it out now where is the map well here is
the map and let's let's go into the
mystery the question of the origins of
the Indian
people so to the best of our
knowledge the best information that we
have says
that about 75 70 maybe 80,000 years ago
there was a migration of human beings a
small group of humans out of Africa into
Asia the out of Africa migration this
happened between 70 and 80,000 years
before today maybe 65,000 we don't quite
know what the date was but it it was
about around this time let's say roughly
tentatively 70,000 years before today
and this migration is believed to have
happened around here the straight of Bab
al-mand
the straight of tears essentially it's
called and it's a pretty narrow straight
there are islands here and it's believed
that this is where the crossing happened
a small bunch of people small small
group of people maybe a few hundreds
maybe 200 300 less than a thousand
people they crossed over from Africa
into Asia and at that time these coastal
regions of Yemen see if you look at the
satellite image today it's all yellow
it's all brown it's all ghastly uh
desertified region Right. But back in
the day when this migration happened,
the the the coastal part of the Arabian
Peninsula, the southern part, southeast
part of the Arabian Peninsula was green.
So it had sufficient vegetation to to
sustain the lives of of a small number
of humans. So these humans, they crossed
over into Asia. They traveled eastwards.
They traveled eastwards into Oman. They
went northwards and again at some point
they crossed maybe the straight of
Hormuz and they reached the Balojasthan
region and even there the coastal
regions were green and then they went
eastwards and then they reached the
Indian subcontinent.
So the first place where the out of
Africa migrants permanently settled down
was India because India had this huge
lush gigantic uh geography. It had
plenty of forest. It had plenty of
fertile land. It had all the resources
needed to sustain a gigantic population
not just a few hundreds. And it's a huge
subcontinent. So this is where the out
of Africa migration the the people they
first settled India was the first
founders zone of the out of Africa
migration and from
India these migrants eventually went in
all directions all across the world now
how do we know the story am I not am I
just making up uh a wonderful nice story
is it is it is it that is that what I'm
doing I'm just making up a nice nice
story how do we know it happened in this
way how do we know that the the
migration happened in a certain
direction from a certain place and it
followed a certain route uh
geographically. How do we know this? We
know it because of various factors
including genetics and there are various
genetic lineages that we are aware of uh
and um you know there are so many haplo
groups today. HLO groups are ancient
lineages. uh a haplo group is is essent
essentially uh a group of people who
live today who are all descended from a
single person who was the originator of
a specific genetic mutation. So that's
hlo groups. Now there are two kinds of
haplo groups patrineal hapll groupoups
and matrineal hapll groupoups. Patrineal
hapll groupoups are yna y chromosome
hypoglo groups uh hlo groupoups and
matrinal hapll groupoups are
mitochondrial DNA hloss. The the
mutation happens in the mitochondrial
DNA. So there are various such families
that exist in the world and the oldest
non-African
u haplo groups are all haplo groups that
originated in India. Let me demonstrate
this. We go back to Google. Where is
Google? Our friends. Yes. Okay. Let's go
to Google. Um so there is haplo group F
for instance. It's a patrineal haplo
group. uh
haplo haplo group F haplo group F. Now
guess where this originated? It
originated about 57 to 62,000 years ago
somewhat after the migration and it
originated in India. It's a male uh
haplo group patrineal haplo group. about
95% of non-African patrineal lineages
are descended from Haplo group
F which originated in India. Well that
that's a gigantic clue here right now
HLO groups. Now let's look at a couple
of female haplo groups M and N hlo
groupoups. Okay, first let's look at HLO
group M. It's a human mitochondrial DNA
hlo which once again originates in
India. How old is it? Let's find out how
old it is. Uh about about 55 to 65,000
years ago. Most likely South Asia
obviously you put in some other things
as well. But it is an Indian origin
mitochondrial DNA. Hoglo group. Now
let's look at HLO group
N. Uh HLO group N. One
second. Mitochondrial DNA. Mitochondrial
DNA. Sorry, bro. Okay, here we are. H
group N. Once again you will find that
it originates in
India and even this is so super
ancient 55 to 70,000 years before today
uh and so on. So these are the oldest
genetic lineages not these are the
oldest non-African genetic lineages in
the world. These all originated in
India. So India is the well you could
say the original founders zone of the
out of Africa migrants and from India
people migrated all over the world. Now
if you look at today's Indians who are
we closest genetically closest to. So
once again let's go to Z map. Yes where
is map? We bring
map. So look today we have these
artificially created nations India,
Pakistan, Afghanistan, Nepal,
Bangladesh, Bhutan, Sri Lanka, Maldives
and so on. But overall this region is
called the Indian subcontinent. And look
we Indians who live in the present day
nation of India. We are genetically
closest to the people of the
subcontinent. Okay. All the way from uh
Bangladesh to Afghanistan, Pakistan to
Sri Lanka, Maldives, Nepal and so on.
Outside of the subcontinent, who are the
people that we are genetically the
closest to? Well, out of outside of the
subcontinent, we are closest to the
people of Iran, Tajakistan. I would say
uh to some extent the people of Yemen
who are very closely related to Indians
because of historical reasons. I'll not
go into those right now. And we will
also find that there's significant
Indian origin DNA in nations like
Cambodia, Thailand, Myanmar
um and obviously the Indonesia region.
Obviously it's Indonesia and and so much
more. And
otherwise there is genetic uh affinity
with the people of Europe as well
because of the various Hapl groups that
we share. R1 A1A or RM17 is one of the
major HLO groups. It's the most
successful extended family in human
history and its origin is most likely
India. Okay. Uh it's it's a huge
controversy right now. Uh if if I if I
Google that if I Google the distribution
of uh that HLO group, it it's going to
be very surprising. Okay, let's go to
that R1 A1A
distribution. If we R1 A1, whatever you
want to call it. Here we go. If you look
at the distribution of this HLO group,
well R1A1A conquers the world where you
can see you can see it's a huge
concentration in India and another huge
concentration in Eastern Europe. Uh you
know Russia, Ukraine region, Eastern
Europe, some parts of Germany etc. and
also uh the Houthan and Tibet region for
some strange reason and so on. So uh
yeah so genetically even though these
people some of these well Europeans look
kind of different from us but yet
genetically there is a significant
affinity that we have linguistically as
well and once upon a time culturally and
civilizationally as well. That's a long
long story. Uh so that's the second part
of the question. How did we survive the
ice age? We survived because we are
super resilient. I'll leave it at that.
All right next questions. Now let's get
into geopolitics.
Yes, here we go. Lots of questions about
Trump and the tariffs. Ronak Mandal,
Geopolitical Dubai, Rishab Tar and Arush
Mahajan. How is it possible to counter
Trump's tariffs? Should Bat be concerned
about the tariff war? What's your
opinion on the recent 26% tariffs
imposed by imposed by Trump on India?
What geopolitical implications will it
have? And what do we do? What should we
do in such a situation? And recently
Trump announced reciprocal tariffs on
every other nation and non-nations and
the planet Mars, Jupiter Saturn and
everything uh including India. But he
also stated that India and PM Modi are
good friends of his and he will impose
discounted tariffs on India. What do you
think he will really do and will he
impose discounted tariffs? Uh the words
don't matter in
geopolitics. Right. So that's the big
news the this week, isn't it? The tariff
war. Trump has imposed tariffs on
everybody. absolutely everybody left
nobody out except Russia because there's
nothing left to do with Russia. They
have imposed so many sanctions on Russia
that there is zero trade between the US
and Russia. So there's no point imposing
tariffs. Same with Belarus and some
other nations. So Trump has announced
reciprocal tariffs on various nations
and this includes 26% on goods imported
from India. So let's say an Indian
thing, okay, an Indian item costs $100.
So he's imposed 26% duty on that. So
it's now going to cost $126 in the US.
So it's going to be more expensive for
for Americans to buy that. So it's it's
it's problem for us, right? Because
it'll be hard for harder for us to sell
stuff in the
US. So uh this obviously is going to
place pressure on India and it's going
to place pressure on the so there are
right now these trade negotiations going
on between the US and India. It's an
ongoing bilateral thing, ongoing
bilateral trade negotiations between
India and the US and it's going to play
it's going to place pressure on that.
But um our economy is going to actually
experience limited relatively limited
impact compared to other nations because
first of all
uh because see first of all the the the
tariffs that we impose on the on the US
and its goods are actually very low.
more than 75% of the items we import
from the US we are imposing less than 5%
5% or less tariffs and there's a 25%
left which we can negotiate and all you
know so it's it's not going to be a huge
thing so there's going to be a moderate
economic impact on India because of the
lower tariff rates that we already have
going on compared to various other major
trading partners okay of the US and we
have a significant domestic demand so
even if we are not if we are facing
export pressures
we have import uh domestic demand. So
it's it's not going to be a huge impact
for us but it's going to cast a shadow
on these negotiations that are going on
because the we are we are uh holding
talks on a regular basis for a bilateral
trade agreement between us and the US.
Uh so it's going to impact that for some
for sure. U so now what happens? So
Trump obviously he's open to discussions
with India. He knows that Mr. Modi has
made it very clear that we should talk,
we should negotiate and we should find
the best way forward. We're not
adversaries, we're not enemies. We need
to sit down, talk, work it out. And
Trump is fine with that. So he's open to
discussions with with India and uh so
that's that's what will happen. So the
US is engaged in these discussions with
India and
uh I think this coming week okay there's
going to be
intensified diplomatic engagement
between India and the US and there's
going to be intensified uh trade level
engagement between India and the US and
the aim is to find a common ground. So
it's it's a process. Okay. And India
will definitely consider certain what do
you call concessions
uh on giving access to the Indian market
to the US and the US in exchange might
offer some flexibility on the tariffs
that they'll impose and all that. So the
objective is to avert a significant
trade dispute. We don't want that. And
both sides will have to do some give and
take. India probably will have to go do
some more give because we have less
leverage against a gigantic power like
the
US. So we should not be super concerned
about the tariff war. It is not really
possible to counter the tariffs. If you
impose 26% on me, I'm going to impose
26% on you. It's not doesn't work like
that. We already impose tariffs on s on
various US goods. Most of these tariffs
are like 5% or less. But some tariffs
are more. Okay. Uh so we we we have to
find a negotiated solution. Uh there's
no point doing a trade war. There's no
point being confrontational. The US is
way too powerful us power powerful for
us to engage in a confrontation with. So
I think among of all the countries that
Trump is imposing tariffs on, the
friendliest is India. and the the best
uh potential outcome also uh I think we
are the ones that will get it. So I
think it's going to all hinge on the
negotiations the talks that we have this
coming week and and further and I think
overall we'll find some kind of good
mutually uh acceptable resolution and
and solution to this entire issue. So we
want to have a proper trade agreement
with the US you know a bilateral trade
agreement. So this actually may may
hasten the arrival or the or the signing
uh of such a bilateral trade agreement.
So I think it's nothing we should be
tremendously concerned about. Uh it's
not like he has only imposed these
tariffs on India. He's imposed tariffs
on everybody including what nations you
would call American allies. The EU
nations, NATO nations, Bangladesh,
Pakistan Pakistan. I'm sure he's imposed
something on Pakistan as well and so on.
So uh it's it's he's not singled out
India and uh we're going to work we're
going to find a way through uh
consultations, negotiations and
talks. Pray Paul says with Trump
announcing a reciprocal tariff policy
this week signaling a dramatic shift in
US trade strategy could this trigger a
new wave of global protectionism or even
realign existing trade blocks? How might
countries like India recalibrate their
trade and export positioning in this
emerging scenario? Uh and more
importantly, will this have a lasting
impact on US economic imperialism and
its global leverage? Um yeah, so this is
going to be definitely interesting
what's what's happening. So
look, the economy we've had for a very
long time is a globalized economy more
or less, isn't it? All nations are
integrated together into a single
trading system. We all do exports,
imports and we have various good duties
and stuff, but it's all under
control and it's it's like
uh open markets, free markets, right? A
free free market economy. That's
essentially what the western rules-based
world or rules-based global order has
been. The effort to impose a you know
free market kind of system on the whole
world where everybody trades with
everybody. So I don't have to
manufacture everything. I can just
import it from wherever it's
manufactured and I'll you know so if I
don't have some things it doesn't matter
because I can import those things and
whatever other nations need I can export
that to them. So it's it's a very open
system. It's been a very open system a
very globalized system. Now Trump has
has imposed tariffs on
everybody. This is essentially the end
of the global system, the globalization
system. It's no longer a free market.
It's now a mercantalist market.
Everybody's going to fight everybody
else through uh you know mercantalist
mercantalist uh strategies and tactics.
Mercantalism is
essentially an economic means of
essentially beggaring your neighbor.
Turn your neighbor into a beggar by, you
know, by having these predatory policies
and all that. So that's what it is. So
what is happening right now? What is
Trump doing? I mean, people are saying
he's gone
mad. He's gone mad, is he? No. This is a
complete This is the beginning
of a restructuring of the global order.
So we are now
witnessing the beginnings of a bipolar
or tripolar world. The multipolarity
will not last too long. From my
perspective, multipolarity, real
multipolarity means 20 nations with
nuclear weapons, which will never
happen. If it happens, it's it's going
to be chaos. Um, so we're going to have
bipolarity or tripolarity. What's what
what do what do I mean by bipolarity?
It's the US empire and its
minions and the Russia China uh
access and in the Russia China access
you will have nations like North Korea
like like uh uh Iran and various other
nations who might want to be in that
grouping and then there may be a third
grouping which is the so-called global
south led by nations like India nations
that want to be neither here nor there
who want to be friends with
There may be a place for such a grouping
in this emerging world order but right
now we are witnessing a rapid shift
global shift and what the US is doing.
So we are witnessing the beginning of a
new cold war the cold war hasn't really
started yet it's it's beginning now. So
in a cold war what you do let's say you
have two major players in a cold war two
major adversaries two superpowerless
superpowers let's say what they do what
each does is that they try to bring all
the supply chains all the production
facilities all the trade networks
everything under their complete control.
So you'll have two systems like this,
two sets of supply chains, two sets of
integrated supply chains, integrated
with with production facilities and
integrated with trade networks and all
that. So China and Russia will do one of
those things and the US and its minions
will do the the other
one. So u the US is right now
uh forcing nations to make a choice.
Okay. uh Canada, Mexico, all the EU
nations, all the NATO nations, they are
being bullied right now, but they're
going to have to make a choice. So, in
the old order, you know, in the old
order, you you could do whatever you
wanted. You you could
have you could buy oil and gas from one
one part of the world. You could access
markets wherever you wanted. American
markets, Indian markets, Chinese
markets. And you and the European
nations could at the same time while
doing all this while enjoying Saudi and
Russian oil and gas
and enjoying access to American and
Chinese and Indian markets, they could
still benefit from the US security
umbrella. And the Americans paid
everything for the security umbrella.
Now that's gone. Now they can no longer
enjoy all those benefits. the European
nations. They can no longer enjoy cheap
Russian
energy, cheap Russian gas or oil. They
can no longer enjoy access to the
Chinese market if they want the benefit
of the American security umbrella. And
if they want the American security
umbrella, they'll have to pay top dollar
for it. They'll have to ramp up their
spending on GDP to 5%. Spending on
military on on the military to 5% of
GDP. So they are all being made to make
a
choice. Okay. Now nations like India may
have a third option and we could be
strategic strategically autonomous. We
could be friends with everybody if we
play the game right. So that is what's
happening right now. So the Americans
are are forcing. So Trump essentially is
is setting has set this thing in motion
through the tariffs and through so much
more. So we are now once again entering
a cold war
era. Um and Russia and China are on one
side. Iran is with them. North Korea is
with them. Uh Japan is trapped in a very
strange geographic neighborhood
uh being an ally of the US. Of course
it's across the Pacific, so it's kind of
fine. And Hawaii is nearby, Guam is
nearby. They have reasonable protection.
But yeah, you have Russia and China
right next door for Japan's
perspective. So, uh for
India, what we need to do is
uh make sure the Americans aren't too
displeased.
Uh you know, have trade talks with them,
hammer out an agreement, find places,
find areas of of uh of convergence and
work it out. work out the best possible
arrangement when it come when it comes
to trade and tariffs. Obviously, the
Americans will demand access to this and
access to that and more whatever they
want. So, we may have to give into some
of these things, but that's how it works
in the world. Okay? Uh it doesn't mean
we're giving up our sovereignty. It's
it's just that we are, you know,
changing some parameters here and there.
Um so from India's perspective it may
still be a good scenario because even
the Chinese want access to the Indian
market and that's why they have changed
their game the past year or so. So it's
it's a wait and watch thing but let's be
very clear a new cold war era is upon
us. The European nations are becoming
very rapidly
irrelevant. Okay. uh they will no longer
be able to uh have these socialistic
policies while being super liberal um
you know welfare state policies. It's
not going to work anymore for them. And
if if they really want to be sovereign,
if they want to stand up the to the US,
they're going to have to become military
powers again, which is very difficult.
And the Americans might not even may not
even allow that. So that's where we are.
So it's a it's a it's a time of very
rapid geopolitical change. A very rapid
geopolitical realignment is happening
right in front of our eyes. And Trump is
actually moving the pieces of the
chessboard in front of us right as we
speak. And we seeing it happen in real
time. We seeing geopolitical realities
change in real time. Usually it takes
decades for this to happen. Nobody
notices what's happening. Right now
we're seeing it on a daily basis. Very
interesting times to live in.
uh Brahar Gupta asks this question.
Let's talk about a hypothetical
question. Let's assume Russia Ukraine
like situation with India and China. If
China wages a war on India, it starts
capturing territories of India with its
big military strength. What will be the
stand of the of Trump in the situation?
Will he act in a similar way and make
some peace deal with with China like
Putin and force India to sign some deal
like the minerals deal with with
Ukraine? Will he force China to return
the captured land back to India or will
he take a completely different stand
from this? I think he will make sure
that we take help from the US instead of
our friend Russia. What lesson can India
learn from today's situation to
safeguard, secure and safeguard itself
from China in the future so we don't
become prey of these powerful countries.
Um foul play of geopolitics. There's no
foul play in geopolitics. Listen, if if
you're powerful, you're going to do
certain things. And I can't blame you
for that. There's no foul play. There's
no right or wrong. There's no good or
bad in geopolitics. There's no right or
wrong in geopolitics. Geopolitics is
amoral. Power is just a number. It's
just a numbers game. So there's no right
or wrong and and foul play. The greatest
sin in geopolitics is
what? It's
weakness. So um to answer your question,
let me uh bring your
attention. Okay, let's let's let's put
my own YouTube channel on the screen.
And
uh let's let's search for something. Uh
the question
is yeah this question right? Will
America
help India. If you search for this
question you get this video. Will it's
it's from about a year ago. I'll not
play it over here. Will America help
India in a war with China? It's a
geopolitical analysis video. Now, let's
just uh copy the let's copy the
transcript of this video and place it
into our friend chat GPT and let's see
what chat GPT has to say about this.
chatgpt.com. One second, let me put
chatgpt on the screen and we will ask
chat GPT to give an overview of the
transcript.
Please give an overview of the
of the below transcript in
bullet. Transcript in bullet
points. Not that. Okay. One second. This
one. Bullet
points. Bang. Okay. Okay, let's see what
Chad Jerry has to say about what I said
a year ago.
Okay, so here's an overview.
Hypothetical India China war. The
scenario starts with a potential future
war initiated by China where India might
need US help if its sovereignty and
territory are at risk and China would
likely seek to capture Indian
territories like Arunachal Pradesh and
Tawang. US help with conditions. The US
would agree to help but would impose
strict conditions essentially
compromising India's sovereignty. Key US
demands would include US military bases
along India's northern border with
Tibet. Permanent US military presence in
India after the war. Access to Indian
military and naval bases, air strips and
control over key military
installations. Economic and political
demands. India must support US sanctions
against Russia. Stop purchasing Russian
oil and weapons and allow US inspections
of Indian weapons. India would have to
freeze its nuclear and missile programs
and allow US nuclear weapons on it on
Indian soil. India would need to become
a formal US military ally and open its
markets to US companies. Trade barriers
with the US would be removed and US
companies could operate freely in India.
India would be required to normalize
relations with Pakistan potentially
reimposing article 370 in Kashmir.
Social and diplomatic influence the the
US would demand roll back of Indian
restrictions on foreign funded NGOs and
allow US diplomats to engage with local
politicians. US experts would be allowed
to reform India's education system
promoting American values and
ideologies. sovereignty loss. These
demands was would effectively strip
India of its sovereignty aligning more
it more with the US influence similar to
NATO members Japan and South Korea which
are not sovereign at all. Historical
context this situation is compared to
historical instances of British
imperialism like their intervention in
Manipur in the 19th century which led to
the downfall of both Manipur and Burma.
India's sovereignty. India is described
as a truly sovereign nation because it
is not subjected to external demands
like other nations. India must continue
strengthening its own defense and
deterrence systems to avoid such a
scenario with China. Conclusion, the
speaker stresses that India in its
current state does not have military
allies and is alone in its defense which
is a part of its
sovereignty and it emphasizes the
importance of maintaining sovereignty
and avoiding dependence on external
powers like the US in the event of a
conflict with China. That's what Chad
Japeti has to tell you as a summary of
that video that I made about a year or
so ago. So that's the answer to your
question. I took the transcript of my
own video put into and that's the
overview it gave me the summary it gave
me. So the answer to your question is
that if such a thing happens and if
India is so weak that China takes over
our territories then the Americans will
be very happy to help. will first wait
for India to become substantially
weakened and they will wait until China
takes big chunks of territory. Then they
will come and offer help. Yes, of
course, we can help and then they will
extract immense concessions which
effectively reduces India to a state to
the state of a nation like Japan which
is under US military occupation or South
Korea or the NATO states less than NATO
actually less sovereignty than NATO.
That's what they would do. It would be
the end of Indian sovereignty. The
Americans would take over. It will be
like British occupation all over
again. So, so what should India do to
ensure this doesn't
happen? Build up our strength. That's
what we need to do. We need to build up
our strength across all domains.
Economic domain, military domain, within
the military domain. We need to build up
various kinds of abilities,
capabilities. We need to have a
stockpile of let's say a few maybe 10,
20, 30,000 missiles. A few hundred
missiles will do
nothing. Oh, we have placed an order for
200 new missiles. What the hell will 200
missiles
do? What does 200 missiles do? What does
300 missiles do? You need a stockpile of
tens of thousands of missiles. learn
from the Ukraine war how many missiles
are being spent on a daily basis or or
historically the past three years or how
many missiles have been fired per day
you need a stockpile of tens of
thousands of missiles to be relatively
safe so that's one thing you need you
need to invest in drone technology the
latest cutting edge drone technology you
need to invest in EI enabled you know
battle space awareness capabilities you
need the best fighter planes at least
good fighter planes large numbers not
like the tiny numbers we have today. We
need to have a much larger naval uh
footprint and much better uh distributed
lethality than we have right now. So
much more. So we need to build up the
economic and military muscle to ensure
that nobody dares to look in our
direction with uh nefarious intentions.
That's what we need to do. You know the
privilege that comes with being a
sovereign nation is that you are
alone. Okay. And that's the way to
be. Right. Next question. Mr. Atus says,
"What do you make of Muhammad Yunos's
statement about India's far east states
being landlocked and inviting China to
extend their interests through
Bangladesh? Is there any action that we
can take against the against them aside
from doing
karinda? So Muhammad Yunus was in um was
in China recently. He's the puppet
figurehead leader of Bangladesh, US
installed puppet leader. Uh I don't know
what his title is. He's not the prime
minister. He's just a figurehead. He's
just a talking head installed by the
Americans. But he's a great man because
he's got a Nobel prize or whatever. So
Yunus goes to China and he offers
Bangladesh's mercenary services to
China. He says that you know India's far
eastern he calls it northeast.
Northeastern states are a landlocked
country. Sorry region. That's what he
said. He said he first said country then
he said region and he says that
Bangladesh guards the the ocean and
India can't reach the ocean from that
region because of us. So China should
invest in Bangladesh. So he's
essentially trying to position China
against India. He's trying to offer his
mercenary services, his nation's
mercenary services uh against India in
in in containing India to China. Uh that
shows his mindset. See, essentially
people like him, they don't produce any
value for society. They don't create
anything good for the country. All they
do is pedal their country to the highest
bidder. That's what they
do. Okay. So he is an US appointed
puppet. But right now he is he was
trying to pedal his country for a few
for a few pieces of silver to
China and he is positioning India as the
enemy right so he tells you about his
mindset so what action can we take
against him against this apart from
doing karininda first of all we should
not do karininda which is you know um
condemnation just ignore his statement
which is what India's government has
done I I don't think we have put out any
statements again about about this
secondly You don't understand that his
words are also just words,
right? His words are also words and they
have exposed his mindset and they have
exposed the nature of his
government. So,
uh first thing we have to remember he is
a figurehead with zero power. All he all
his job is to stay in the
limelight. Draw all the media attention
to himself so that the people who are
really in power, they can stay hidden.
That's his job. And who's really in
power in Bangladesh? It's the military.
It's always the military. So the
military, Bangladesh is in the military
role. And the military is aligned with
the
US and Muhammad is trying to sell his
country to China. What should India do?
India should not do Karininda. India
should also not take any take any
drastic action. Be aware that this is a
very hostile Bangladeshi regime. aware
be aware that this is East Pakistan
again and take the you know required
measures along the border regions
uh be aware that you may have uh
anti-India elements propping being
propped up again in these regions maybe
terrorists from Pakistan you know
Pakistani people brought into Bangladesh
to u you know to introduce terrorism
into India Indian parts across the
border or something else. So always be
aware of these things and take adequate
measures to ensure that none of this
spills over into India. And when the
time is right, we
can we can perhaps uh uh encourage
Bangladesh to to revert to a better form
of governance, a more democratic form of
governance. We can do it eventually at
some point in time. So that's what we
should do. But we should know that by
now it should be clear Muhammad is an
enemy. Okay. Tidik 73 says, "You stay
away from Poland. Do not talk rubbish
that Poland might get involved in
Ukraine." Why are people getting
upset? I said I talked rubbish that
Poland might get involved in Ukraine.
Okay, let's
let's Poland prepares for war with
Russia. Okay, let's see. Let's let's put
this on the screen. So I'm talking
rubbish that Poland is u might get
involved in Ukraine. Okay, look at this.
This is from the Jamestown Foundation
which is a very very highly regarded
think tank or
organization. And the title of this
document, this article is Poland
prepares for for direct war with Russia
by Yanush Bugashki. The date is April 4,
2025, which is yesterday, 23 hours ago.
He wrote this executive summary. Poland
is accelerating its military buildup for
a projected war with Russia as Ukraine
faces a potentially unfavorable outcome
in the peace talks brokered by the
Donald Trump administration. Wow.
Everything I've been saying for the past
3 years is coming true, right? So, Warso
plans to introduce voluntary military
training for all adult males and bolster
Poland's armed forces to half a million
half a million military personnel and
reserveists in addition to increasing
military spending and urging NATO allies
to raise their defense
budgets and so on. So you can see Poland
is preparing for a direct war with
Russia. This is all happening in the
context of the Ukraine
war. So there you have it. Am I talking
rubbish? I look you make projections
based on the
situation and these projections are are
made based on just
calculations and historical
facts. There's no emotion involved in
this. I'm sure you were from Poland,
sir. That's why you got upset. But there
you have it. What I just showed you is
that Poland is preparing for direct war
with Russia. I think just a day or so
after you you made this comment, we get
the situation. So I apologize if I upset
you, but facts are facts and facts don't
care about anyone's feelings. And that's
what's actually happening. And it's it's
silly. It's stupid of Poland to provoke
Russia if it's trying to provoke Russia.
Of course, Poland should be prepared for
all eventualities. Poland has uh seen a
lot of bad situations in the past, past
70, 75, 80 years, we know what happened.
So Poland should be prepared and when
you have a gigantic more powerful
neighbor next door, kind of next door,
almost next door, you should be
prepared. So yeah, you should prepare
for war. If if you should have all the
preparations uh ready, I would say uh
and Poland is in some way or the other
already involved in Ukraine as well.
So it's just a fact. Sorry.
Okay, Abishek Ja says a very uh thank
you so much. I really appreciate that
sir. Uh the question is has the Indian
government made the Indian economy
sanction proof from the US? Uh it is
said that we purchased Iranian oil and
made payments for it not in US dollars
but through various humanitarian aids.
Also it's said that many ruby rupee
rubal yuan trades have and are taking
place completely ignoring the need for
the dollar. is this true and so on.
Okay, the the the core question is is
India sanction proof and when we talk
about sanctions we're talking about US
sanctions. So let me put something on
the screen which happened just a few
months ago less than 6 months
ago. Here's this article India response
to US sanctions against 19 companies
over support for Russia. So in November,
the Biden regime imposed sanctions on
against nearly 400 individuals and
entities including 21 from India for
supporting Russian military efforts amid
the war in Ukraine. So the Americans
impose sanctions on India and various
Indian entities 21 Indian 19 21 whatever
it is in November. So the Americans can
impose sanctions at will whenever they
feel like. uh they the they imposed
sanctions on India in what 1998 after we
uh tested nuclear weapons and I can
assure you we are not sanction sanction
proof the if they if the Americans
hypothetically in in an alternate
universe decide to
impose on India the kind of sanctions
they have currently imposed on Russia
it'll destroy the Indian economy
completely destroy the Indian
economy so India is not sanction proof
please be aware of
Ronach says, "Do you think with the
current bureaucracy that India has, can
we seriously grow as a civilization and
a country to a great extent?" Uh, the
answer to your question is no. With the
kind of bureaucracy that we have and
with the kind of system that we have, we
cannot grow as a
civilization. We are not a civilization
today. the way it is defined in the in
in in the context of the current
governance system and all that it
doesn't define India as a civilization
it just it just defines India as a as a
nation state okay and uh even as a
nation state you can't progress much
with the kind of system we have and the
kind of bureaucracy we have so the
answer to your question is no we can't
progress we can't we can't seriously
grow as a nation as a country with the
kind of bureaucracy and the kind of
system that we have Today it's
impossible. Sayan syanthan bis says why
does India lack manufacturing base like
China? Is it true that manufacturing
power provides better employment than
service sectors? If so, why? Uh
manufacturing provides look uh
manufacturing why why does India lack
the kind of manufacturing base that
China has? Okay, imagine that you want
to manufacture something. Let's say you
want to manufacture
pencils. There's a huge demand for
pencils. Let's say in the US in in
Europe. So, you want to manufacture
pencils. So, you say, "Okay, great idea,
great opportunity. There's this
opportunity for this big demand. So,
let's let's uh fulfill the demand. Let's
set up a manufacturing plant for pencils
in whatever state you are in."
So first question, you will need
money, right? To set up a manufacturing
plant. Second, you'll need land. How
easy is it to get money? Let's say you
are just a guy with an idea. Okay, but
you've got a viable business
plan. So you should be able to go to a
bank. You've got a great business plan
and the bank should look at your
business plan, look at your credentials
and determine whether you are a person
who can make it this work. And if they
think they can you can make it work,
they should give you a loan for the
amount of money that you that you need,
right? Is this process easy in India?
No, it's super difficult. It's very hard
for anyone to raise money. You can go to
venture capital and all but those
people, many of them allegedly are like
sharks,
predators. Uh the government should help
like like the Chinese government helps.
In China, if you have a great business
plan, if you if you want to do something
good, uh you'll get the money, you'll
get the funds, you'll also get the land.
They will give you the best possible
land for your venture. In India, getting
land is a miserable experience. And then
there's all the regulatory mess. You get
you need permissions and approvals and
certificates and rubber stamps and you
have to deal with the entire
bureaucratic
maze. So many different levels of
approvals. You need so many officials.
You have to go to personally. Nothing is
online. You go and meet people in
person. When you meet people in person,
you have to do other things as well.
offer allegedly offer bribes allegedly
and so on. So before you start anything,
if you have to start offering allegedly
bribes allegedly, then what profit will
you ever make? And if it takes so long,
if it is so difficult, so tedious, so
painful to just start a business, why
would anybody start a business? And in a
place like China, you can get it done
like that.
So that's why India lacks a
manufacturing base unlike China. That's
why in India everybody if you want to
have a startup it should be all online
where you don't need any approvals
should be an app or something that you
can just click just you know tap on the
app and do whatever Swiggy or Zumato or
Flipkart or whatever right or whatever
those apps are you know you know what
what is it uh Blinket Zeppto Denzo order
order whatever you want at home and
you'll get it in 10 15 minutes that that
sort of stuff works in India
But
manufacturing for that you need real
world stuff. You need real money. You
need real land. And doing all that is
super super difficult in India. So it's
because of the system that India is not
a manufacturing
power. It's because of the system. The
system is designed to prevent India from
being imagine this. The system is
designed to prevent India from being a
great manufacturing power. The system is
designed to keep India
mediocre. My question is why isn't the
system being
reformed? It's because the
people you know I'm not talking about
the highest levels but
overall the people who are part of the
system they benefit from the system.
Overall, the people who are part of the
system, who are in power, allegedly
politicians, allegedly bureaucrats,
allegedly whoever else, people who are
part of the system, they allegedly
benefit from the system. And it is in
their interest to keep the system the
same way it is and don't allow it to
change. If it becomes transparent, if it
becomes system that serves the nation
and the people, then how will it serve
them? Vested interests,
right? So that's why it doesn't change.
And when a
system it behaves in a way that it is
not supposed to behave, its stated
purpose is X but its
actual the way it actually behaves is
not X but Y. It's called
corruption. Right? That's a definition
of corruption. Um so yeah that's why
India is not progressing. That's why
India isn't doing great. India has the
the the potential to become the the next
manufacturing superpower. If you just
reform the system, if you just make all
these things easy, if somebody has a
great idea and has the business acumen
behind it, then give the person the
funding, give the take a risk on the
person, give the person funding, give
the person land, give them one chance
and let's see how it goes. And as long
as your vetting process is good, you'll
find the good people, the right people,
you'll give money to the right people.
Now, obviously, everybody has ideas. It
doesn't mean everybody should be given
money. the right people should be given
money and there there's plenty of the
right people in this country but yeah
because of the way the system is India
lacks the manufacturing base because the
system is designed to prevent India from
becoming a great nation imagine that so
why isn't it being reformed because
allegedly the people within the system
benefit from the system and because it's
benefiting them they don't care if it is
hampering if it is hurting the
country that's the story of India 70
years 75 years whatever it
Uber says ancient civilizations like
China, India, Rome, present day Italy
continue to live on. Rome doesn't live
on as a civilization. Rome died a long
time ago and I'll come to that why.
Okay, let's continue. China considers
itself as a civilization even today.
India as at least per the constitution
is a nation state. As per the
constitution of India, India is not a
civilization. India is a mere nation
state as per our constitution. Okay. The
constitution that has been imposed on
India
undemocratically. So is this one of the
problems? The way we are perceived and
the way we project ourselves which
becomes an impediment in our
growth. Right? So so that's the
question.
Um so if you look at the constitution of
India you will see that u it it is it
uh the constitution of India defines
India as India that is bat and something
or the other okay and it does not define
India as a civilization it defines India
as a nation state now Rome no longer
exists Rome is Italy Italy is a
Christian nation Italy is a non-s
sovereign nation part of NATO part of EU
it's not neither a civilization today
because okay so then the question to
understand why Rome is not a
civilization today we have to understand
what is a
civilization so take
notes a civilization is an advanced
society which has a certain set of
characteristics first characteristic it
has a highly
evolved and institutionalized indigenous
culture
institutionalized indigenous
culture. Italy is a Christian nation.
Christianity is not indigenous to Europe
to to Italy, but it's in
institutionalized into Italy. So that's
number one. So
um for example, in the Arabic nations,
their
culture/religion is Islam and that's
part of the
institutions, that's part of their legal
system, it's part of their education
system, it's part of their governance
system. It's part of everything. So it's
institutionalized. Now ask yourself this
about India. India's indigenous culture,
the Dharmic culture. Is it
institutionalized anywhere? Is it
institutionalized in the in the
judiciary? No. The judiciary is based on
the European system, the western system,
the western constitution and the western
legal system. You can give it some
Indian name bhat sahita or whatever but
it's still a western code of law right
so it's not institutionalized in the
judiciary is the Indian uh cultural
civilizational system dharmic system
instit institutionalized in the
education system it's not our education
is completely secular completely
western so there we have it even we are
not a civilization today okay now you
need to have laws constitution
institutions that are grounded in bas in
the indigenous culture and indigenous
values, indigenous ethics, indigenous
morality. We don't have any of that. We
need had for a civilization for you to
be a civilization, you need to have an
indigenous system of governance. We have
copied copypasted the Westminster model
from the United Kingdom the
parliamentary system which is not suited
for for a country like India for a for a
gigantic subcontinent sized entity as
India we don't have an indigenous system
of governance we've lost it so we don't
even have that then you need a strong
civilization a single civilizational
language we used to have it it was
called Sanskrit
we have ditched it. Right? Then you need
to have a big geographical area. You
need to have a powerful economy, a large
military, high levels of prosperity. We
have some of these. We don't have high
levels of prosperity. We have a
reasonably powerful military. We have a
cumulatively large economy, but it has
problems.
And for you to be a civilization, you
need to have a large sphere of economic,
military and cultural influence that
extends significantly beyond your
borders. We don't have that. A
civilization has has its own language.
It has its own
script. And a civilization has its own
calendar system of
timekeeping. We use a foreign calendar
today. We use everything foreign. And a
civilization is a net exporter of
culture. India today is a net absorber
of culture. We export nothing
culturally. So you see that you see
what's happening here from from a when
you define something properly you will
say that India is no longer a
civilization
today. India is culturally and
civilizationally vasalized
today. And the root
cause multiple root causes the
constitution is is is a big issue. the
constitution defines everything that
comes under it, the judiciary and
whatever else and laws and all that. So
yeah, so many issues we have
today. So China is China a civilization
in its own right. China also has a legal
system that's somewhat based on the
western system. They they have copied
their education system from from the
west. They have chosen to be a
technically a socialist country which is
again a non-Chinese thing. But overall
it is still very uh it it is more
indigenously civilizational than India
is China. Rome no question it is not a
civilization. It's not even a sovereign
nation. India is a sovereign nation but
India has chosen to no longer define
itself as a civilization. It has chosen
to throw away all the aspects of
civilization it had and it's actively
derinating its population through the
education system, through the media,
through the through the entertainment
industry, through everything else to
completely forget what a culture is. So
no, India is on the way to becoming a
non-ivilizational
entity. Okay,
Nillehani. Okay, let's talk about
Nilani. So Mohit Chri says, "What's your
take on the recent idea of tokenization
of land by Nandan Nilakhani and Prren
Paul says Nandanda Nilakani's push to
tokenize land assets raises serious
questions given his past remarks against
India building core LLMs and Morti's
take on nationalism? Is this another
steps to shift control of a
civilizational asset like land into
centralized or foreign hands? Also since
land is a state subject could this tempt
regional parties to rush adoption
without debate? Is this a digital trap
masters
progress? So Mr. Nille Khani uh recently
spoke about he proposed the idea of uh
tokenization of
land. So the the his proposal for the
tokenization of land. It it aims to
digitize India's land ownership rights
land ownership rights. It wants to
digitize them by converting them into
blockchain based tokens. Now I'll not go
and explain what blockchain is and how
it works. But there's something called
blockchain based tokens and he wants to
digitize land ownership rights by
converting it into blockchain based
tokens. So by doing this he seeks to uh
unlock see land
is about half of India's wealth is
approx is is estimated to be in the form
of land okay but this wealth is not a
liquid
asset it's not like like cash right you
can spend if you got a let's say if you
go if you have a one lakh rupees in a
bank account you can spend 10 rupees
today or 200 rupees or whatever whatever
you wish to but if you have a a block of
land you can't just uh you know sell it
off piece by piece or any of that
doesn't work like that it's not a liquid
asset okay so about half of India's
wealth is in the form of land and it's
not a liquid asset there are legal
restrictions on it that sometimes you
have situations where the where the
title isn't unclear and so on so forth
so says that this enormous economic
potential of India's land assets is
frozen because of all these issues so
let's tokenize it. So if you tokenize
land, it will make these assets
tradable. So if you're an owner who has
a certain amount of land, you will be
able to
trade sell parts of the land. You'll be
able to fractionalize ownership of the
land. You can you'll be able to lo use
that land as collateral for a loan. So
you know this can give this can bolster
entrepreneurship. It can it can bolster
economic growth especially in rural
areas where you have lots of problems.
So one of the good things this can uh um
one of the good effects it can have is
that it can unlock all this all this
frozen wealth this dormant wealth. It
can transform this idle land assets into
active financial resources. So if you're
a land owner you can access capital for
business ventures or investments or
whatever. Right? So by making it
tradable your land becomes a liquid uh
asset and uh that's good for you. You
can have fractional ownership. So you
can have multiple multiple investors to
own shares in a property. So that's
good. So it it you know real estate is
is something that very few people have
access to. So it can democratize access
to real estate investment. It can reduce
barriers for small investors. And
blockchain technology is is secure. it
it uh the record keeping is secure and
it reduces fraud and all that. So that's
another uh plus point. But there are
issues with this uh proposal. H what are
the
issues? Look imagine you have a person
who lives in a small village h and that
person u has a gambling problem. the
person has a drug problem or the person
has alcohol problem is an alcoholic and
you know how how people with these
issues are they need cash they they they
always need cash they're always looking
for cash to get the next high or get the
next whatever right so if your land
becomes a liquid
asset then such people could just
impulsively sell off their
assets which would make their financial
situation much worse. It could make
their financial instability even more
instable, right? So there are many
people in rural rural areas who have
these addiction problems and all that.
So they could be very easily exploited
by making their land tradable and and
and converting land into a liquid asset
and you know so that's one issue. Then
the the liquification financialization
of land, it could very rapidly result in
the in the concentration of even that
wealth
um in the hands of large entities, large
corporations and it would it can very
rapidly marginalize small land
owners. For a few rupees they'll they'll
sell off their land to a big
corporation. So eventually you may end
up with just like five or six
corporations who land who who own 80% of
the land in India. You may end up in a
situation like that. Do you want
that? And and so on. And there are
security concerns with uh with cy with
with blockchain, you know, cyber
attacks, the theft, all that. There are
some uh concerns about that also. So
there are various issues like this.
Okay. The main issue is that uh it could
lead to the exploitation of small land
owners in rural areas who may very
quickly be induced to to divest to to
sell off their land and then they're
left with nothing. you know um there was
a time in in in India maybe about a
thousand years ago before the Turkish
invasions where everybody had land
India's population would have been about
300 400
million and everybody had land land that
was uh in the possession of their uh
family and ancestors
for for generations dozens of
generations everybody had their own land
then what happens is that the the Turks
slowly took over India They got they
they they they stole all the
land. They uh divested Indians of their
land ownership. They instituted the
Zagindari
system which took away the land of the
of the indigenous people. Then you had
the British who came in who imposed the
riatwari act and so on so forth. And as
a as a consequence of this most Indians
today don't have any land of their
own. And if you still have some land
some ancestral land somewhere consider
it to be a privilege.
And when people like Mr. Nilleani come
up with these ideas, they essentially
want to induce people to sell off that
land to they want to convert it into a
liquid asset that can be you know traded
like like shares on the stock market.
Today somebody is the owner, next day
somebody else is the owner. That's not
how land ownership
works. Maybe he's framing it as a good
idea that you know it will uh bolster
entrepreneurship and and so on so forth
in in rural areas. But I think we have
to be very careful about these
proposals. So from my perspective, it's
not a very good
idea. I'm very skeptical about
this. Uh and land as a state subject.
Look, I will not speculate about whether
regional parties would want to rush into
adoption without a debate. I'm not sure
about that. But this is what I have to
say say about this matter.
Uh, Lipton Barua says, "I am one of the
descendants from Arakhan Chittagong
region currently living in
Dargiling. Our king from Chittagong
wrote a letter to India about joining
India. Mr. Patel was interested but Mr.
Neu and Mr. Gandhi betrayed
us." Well, well, well, well, well, well.
I would like to I I I'll do some I'll
have to do some research about this. Uh,
I haven't heard of this matter before.
We know of many uh kings who signed the
uh instrument of accession that for
example the Khan of Kalat in
Baljasthan he signed the instrument of
accession but Mr. Neu rejected it and
did not allow Baljasthan to become part
of India. So now when there are many
other examples of this Mr. Neu
repeatedly rebuffed the Maharaja of
Kashmir's
uh offer to join India multiple times at
least three times before finally uh
asking Mount Batan to agree to accept
it. So Mr. Neu has done lots of things
that don't make sense to small less
intelligent people like
us. Um but now we hear this now. So the
king from Chetakong wanted to join
India. Mr. Patel was interested but Mr.
Nehu and Mr. Gandhi both apparently
betrayed the people of Chetakong. I'll
have to look into this but wow. Okay,
one more such instance comes in. When
someone wants to join your nation, why
do you say no? I don't get it.
Well, uh I I will certainly do my own
due diligence, my own research on this,
but uh I would like to thank Lipton Bara
for bringing this to our notice. Very
interesting. Very interesting
indeed. Okay. I don't know how to read
this. I there was a time when I could
read Arabic, but I've lost the practice.
I I learned the Arabic script over one
afternoon when I was a teenager. I had a
dictionary. That was the Arabic script
and uh yeah I learned how to write write
and read in Arabic over one afternoon's
time. So the question is uh can you let
us know if Iraqi Arabs in Iraq are
native Mesopotamians because I've heard
that they are Arabized Iraqi Arabs who
were forced into Arab culture and Islam.
I have seen Iraqi Arabs DNA showing they
have more Mesopotamia Mesopotamian DNA
than Arab, but I don't know of its real
results.
Well, that's a very interesting
question. I personally haven't done
research into this matter, but let's
take a look at the map and talk about
and see uh what's what is the region
that we are referring to over here.
Mesopotamia. Iraq, right? Okay, let's go
to the map. We go to Iraq. What is
Mesopotamia? First of all, for those who
don't know, Mesopotamia is this region
between two rivers, the Tigris and the
Euphrates.
Okay, that's what Mesopotamia is. It's a
very fertile region. If you look at the
the city of Baghdad, the river that
flows through it is called the
Tigris. And if you go to a different
part of Iraq, you will have a different
river called the
Euphrates. Okay, this is the
Euphrates. So, if you look at a
satellite image of Iraq, it's pretty
dry, right? Isn't it? But you have this
greenish region which is the region
between the the two great rivers and
that region is called Mesopotamia. The
region between two great two two rivers
uh the Tigress and the
Euphrates. So now the people so now this
place is called
Iraq and
uh and the question is what's the origin
of the people of Iraq? Essentially if
you look at the if you look at Iraq
today everyone speaks Arabic. Everybody
essentially mostly most people are
Muslims. You al you do have Kuresh
people. You do have uh people and so on.
Those are small minorities reasonably
small minorities but most people are are
uh they are Muslims apart from the even
the Kar Muslims uh most people speak
Arabic and uh most people identify as
Arabs. But are the Iraqis really Arabs?
because
um even the Egyptians are considered to
be Arabs today. They're part of the
Arabic Arab world, right? But if you
look at the map, Arabia is this
peninsula here which is now called Saudi
Arabia. So Udi Arabia and you have
Yemen, Oman and the UAE, that's also
part of it. Uh so that's the region
where the Arabs historically lived and
Mesopotamia was different. Mesopotamia
was west of the subcontinent, west of
Iran, west of Persia essentially. And we
in India used to pray trade with
Mesopotamia and the Mesopotamia gave
rise to multiple great civilizations.
The Sumerians, the Acadalians, Assyrians
and so on. These were
non-Arabic cultures.
Now I haven't really studied the DNA or
uh you know uh studies researches about
this matter but u I am pretty sure that
the u descendants of the Sumerianss the
Assyrians the Acadians
uh and so on they still exist they still
live and they probably uh have been
assimilated into Arabic culture that is
probably most likely what happened
u they had to accept the culture and the
religion that the Arabs brought into the
region. The same thing happened to the
Persians. If you look at Persia, Iran
today about half of Iran is ethnically
Persian and uh they have obviously uh
they today practice many of them
practice uh the religion and the culture
that was brought by the Arabs. They
don't speak the Arabic language. That's
one thing they have preserved. But in
nations in parts of the world like Iran,
in Syria, Jordan, Egypt, everyone speaks
Arabic. Even in the northern African
nations like Libya, Algeria, Morocco,
etc. So it's it's part of the spread of
Arabic conquests in this part of the
world. I am pretty sure that if you
study if if these studies have been done
then you will find that the people of
Iraq many of them have the original uh
ancestry still in them Mesopotamian
ancestry. I'm pretty sure about that. I
haven't done the research myself. Now is
not the time to do it live or because I
have so many questions to answer but I
am pretty sure and it's a very
interesting question that someone from
this region is asking. I'm pretty sure
that if you actually look at the
genetics, the DNA, then the ethnicities
will be different from the Arabic
ethnicity in the Mesopotamia and Iraq
region. Even Jordan, even Syria, even
Egypt, for sure the people of Egypt,
most of them will still be descendants
of the ancient Egyptians even though
they today speak the Arabic language and
uh practice the Arabic religion, Islam,
right? Okay. Next question is by Abanu.
Abimmanu Sharma. Why was the Mongol
invasion of Japan a failure? How was
Kubla Khan's leadership in contrast to
Chingis
Khan? Okay, the Mongol invasion of
Japan, it was a failure. Now, lots of
people imagine that Chingis Khan tried
to invade Japan and he
failed. Is not the case. Chingis Khan
died in 1227 AD. I believe 1227 AD. And
the Mongol invasions of Japan happened
in the 1270s and 1280s. I think it was
1274 and
1281. Okay. So there were two two
invasions done by the Mongols. Invasions
of Japan, attempted invasions of Japan
and both failed. And if you if you if
you look at the the uh the prevalent uh
mythology, let's say the mythology is
that there was this divine wind that
came and saved Japan both times.
wind brought on by the gods. The kami
the Japanese traditional gods are called
the kami. In the Shinto religion, the
gods are called kami. So this divine
wind is called kami kaz. So it was
divine wind kami kaz that saved Japan
both times and destroyed the invasion
fleet. That's that's one version of then
there is some truth to it for
sure. So here's what happened. It was
the grandson of Shri Chingghis Khan
Kubla Khan Shri Kubla Khan who ordered
the invasions of Japan. So Shri Kubla
Khan ruled China. He was the emperor of
China. He he was the successor of Agodai
Khan I think. So he was the emperor of
China and he wanted to expand his
possessions. So, so he ordered this
first invasion of Japan in 1274
AD. And you'll find that the first
invasion 1274 was probably nothing but a
reconnaissance mission, a probing raid.
It was not aimed at total
conquest. Okay? And it did not really
succeed very well. Uh there is a place
called Hakata Bay. Hakata Bay in Kyushu
in let let's let's go to the map and
that's where the landing attempt was
attempted and it was a failure after
warfare and all that. So uh if you go
here I think it is this
region where is Hakata Bay
uh sorry it's down
here it's in the Fukuoka region. Yeah.
So I think this is this place is called
Hakadab Bay and it is in this region
that the the the landing was attempted
by the uh Mongol ships. So I think the
first time the Mongols uh invaded they
sent in close to a thousand ships. Okay.
And it was a failure.
uh and then in the um and there the when
they tried to retreat from Hakata Bay
that's when uh u a storm happened a
storm set upon the fleet and destroyed a
large portion of the fleet. So it's when
they had already been defeated and they
were withdrawing and after this
invasion and what they did okay what
what the Mongols did is that uh first of
all they had tried to use diplomacy they
had sent emissaries to Japan and uh
demanded that Japan acknowledges the the
supremacy of of Kubla Khan that Kublhan
is our overlord and we are his vassals
and Japan refused that. So after the
diplomacy failed, the invasion was
attempted in 1274. And during the
invasion, the soldiers sent by Kubla
Khan, they massacred civilians and they
massacred monks. They massacred Buddhist
monks. And when you do such things, it's
going to enrage the
samurai, right? So now the samurai were
enraged and they saw these these
soldiers of Kubla Khan as absolute
barbarians and they said we'll fight you
to the to the death and then what they
did is that they built a very large
coastal wall in the Hakata Bay region to
prevent future landings and the samurai
organized themselves very well and they
bolstered their numbers and then u there
was a second invasion in 1271 in 1281
and in the 1281 invasion I think
the Mongols had about 4,000 ships and
more than 100,000 more than a lakh men
according to their records I believe and
uh so they were trying to coordinate
this force from from across the East
China Sea and it was not a very
successful thing uh they had to cross
through as well and so on so once again
uh that invasion did not work very
And there was another storm that that
that came in the way and destroyed a
large portion of the ship. Uh many of
the ships were dashed against rocks and
they were destroyed. So uh there's a
combination of lots of factors. So there
is the the bad weather that the the the
storms uh the Japanese were very well
prepared especially after the first
invasion uh happened. Uh the Mongols
overreached themselves logistically. You
can't go so far and be so out
overstretched. Um the Japanese t tactics
would have been good. The strategies
would have been good because the
Japanese knew their own home conditions.
It's like playing a cricket match on
your home ground versus playing your
match on the on the opponent's ground,
right? So it was home conditions. They
knew what to expect. The Mongols
probably did not have that much uh naval
expertise that that also could be a
factor. Uh and so on. So it's a it's a
combination of lots of factors that uh
caused the failure of both the attempted
invasions 1274 and
1281. I think um ultimately it was about
the Mongols about about Kubla Khan Kubl
Khan being over
ambitious. He was over ambitious. He
tried to project his power into an
completely unfamiliar territory. The
Mongols were well traditionally they
were they were nomads. They were horse
archers. They were unbeatable in that
form of warfare. Now, if you take these
people and you put them on ships and ask
them to invade an island nation, it's
not going to work. It's a super
unfamiliar, super hostile environment.
And who's defending Japan? The samurai.
Come on. It's not not going to work,
right? So it's it's a combination of
these factors that uh caused the failure
of the attempted invasion by Kubla Khan.
How was Kublh Khan's leadership in
contrast to Changis Khan? Changist Khan
and Kublhan were very different
personalities. Uh Changis Khan was well
a military genius probably the greatest
military genius of all time. He
conquered the greatest empire ever
conquered by one man. He conquered more
territory in in in 10 years than than
Roman emperors conquered in 200 years.
So there's that he was a ruthless
organizer, superb
organizer.
Um he he he he believed in merit
meritocracy. He promoted the best most
merito most uh the ones who performed
the best. He as a consequence he had the
best generals. Uh JB Subodai
uh so many more. Subai was probably the
greatest general of all time. Subai
Bhagat and so on. Um and as a ruler, he
was a good ruler. He was tolerant. He
tolerated almost every religion and
everything except maybe one or two which
I will not mention here. Okay? And so
on. So he was he was very very open. Uh
he was very good to the people he
conquered after they were conquered. But
uh if you did something bad to him, he
would not uh let that go and so on.
That's how Chingis Khan
was. Um in contrast to Chingghist Khan,
Kubla Khan did
not Oopsie. What
happened just a
second there seems to be
okay. So yeah, in in contrast with
Chingis Khan, Chingisan ruled from the
horse.
didn't he? Kubla Khan ruled from the
throne and Kubla Khan had he became a
very uh sinusized emperor. He's he ruled
over over China. His focus was not on
conquest. It was mainly on
administration. It was on ruling. He
invested in a postal service. He
invested in the bureau bureaucracy. He
invested in dams. He invested in
architecture. That's the kind of stuff
Kubla Khan invested in. and he and
Chingis Khan invested in other things.
So Chingis Khan whatever he achieved
Kubla Khan wanted to consolidate that
consolidate all of that by civil by by
being a civilizing force but he also at
some point in life would have had that
itch that I too should conquer right at
some point in time something and that's
why he tried probably Japan but it did
not work. So yeah there you have it
that's the difference between the two uh
men very different styles of leadership.
Shivam Johan says, "I am currently doing
my master's degree in history and plan
to do a PhD or pursue a PhD later."
Okay, good, good, good, good. My dream
is to become a great historian and
archaeologist making meaningful
contributions to our understanding of
India's past. I want to focus on
underrated and unexplored areas that
still hold the potential for new
discoveries. What are some lesser
studied topics, regions or periods in
Indian history that I should start
reading about now or and later explore
in
depth? Look, everything is
unexplored. Even if you talk about let's
say talk about the period in India
thousand years ago, just before the Turk
invasions began, ask yourself this
question.
What was a typical day in the life of an
ordinary man or woman in
Bhat in the year 1000
AD? What is a typical day
like? Okay, let's say you're talking
about somebody who lives one person who
lives in the region of Delhi, present
day Delhi, one person who lives in the
region of present day maybe Bangalore or
maybe Chennai, one person who lives in
present day Gujarat, one person who
lives in present day
Assam. Okay. four people north, east,
west and one person who lives in central
India. Five people and we go back a
thousand years. What was a typical day
in the life of a person who lived in
these five parts of India? We don't even
have those answers. What language did
they speak? What was the language spoken
in the Dilli region 1,000 years ago?
What language was spoken in the Assam
region a thousand years ago? In the
Bangalore region a,000 years ago? What
language was spoken in let's say Gujarat
a thousand years
ago? Do we even know that clearly? What
was the the lifestyle like? What was the
dress code like? What dress did they
wear? What language did they speak? What
was a typical day
like? What kind of education did they We
know next to nothing about these
things. There is so much we don't know.
A thousand years before today, we don't
know a lot. 2,000 years before today, we
know even even even less and so on. So
there is so much you can learn. But if
you want to if you talk about talking
about archaeology, I can talk about I
can give you a lot of archaeological
sites that are like you say underrated
or or neglected. For example, in the we
know we have this gigantic dried up
river, right? The Saraspati. She left us
because we not worthy of her perhaps. So
we have this huge dry riverbed that
ranges from the Himalayan region all the
way to the run of Kach and it used to
empty into the Indian Ocean the sea of
Sabarashtra. So along this dry riverbed
the majority of which is in present day
India not in Pakistan. Along this dry
riverbed you have more than 2,000
unexplored archaeological sites from the
Saraswati Synindu time period of our
history.
more than 2,000 unexplored sites. Can
you imagine how much how much
archaeological
uh treasures left uh they are just
waiting for us to uh explore them to
discover them right so there is that you
can explore that once you are an
archaeologist there are obviously sites
like Rakari which is well known now
there is there are the the coastal sites
like
Davira and yeah do is a great one in in
present day Gujarat Okay. In the run of
Kacha region, there is Kalibangan in
Rajasthan. The probably the largest site
that no not the largest site, one of one
of the largest sites we have. Rakari is
the largest one. So, Kalibangan is is
about I don't know how many maybe 3,000
5,000 BC some something like that time.
Then you have places like Ganeshwar in
Rajasthan. Then Soli these days is well
known. Soli in Uttar Pradesh where
that's a bronze age chariot burial site.
Right. There is uh Dhaabad in
Maharashtra. There is a site in Kashmir
called
Burahham which is a very
ancient village kind of site 3,000 BC or
something and it it has it has layers
from different time periods and they
also discovered a carving of of
of a sky chart a star chart in the
Burahham region where you have two suns
in the sky and that's the first ever the
oldest ever depiction of a supernova.
event right. Um then if you go to
eastern India Orisa there is Sushup
Palgar which is a fortress like site
okay very interesting site um maybe
around 500 BC or something around that
time. uh Morian
era there is uh if you go to West Bengal
there is Chundra Chundra Ketugar a
fascinating site where so many
fascinating discoveries have already
been made but it is still like mostly
unexplored there is Kosambi in Uttar
Pradesh wonderful place then there is
AIChatra in Uttar Pradesh the capital of
Panchchal Mahajalapad so if you look for
a Chhatra let me I mean the kind of
architecture you have there let's go to
Google Okay, there is a gigantic
pyramidal temple in
Ahhatra. Uh, sorry, not this. Let's
go. I I want to do a Google search for
AIR. All right. Here we
are.
Okay. Ahi Chhatra. Ahi Chhatra. AI means
serpent. Chhatra means umbrella kind of
thing. So, Ai Chhatra northern Panchchal
capital. It made it back to the
Namhahabara times. And look at this
structure. This is an ancient temple or
stupa or whatever. Look at that. It's
it's a pyramidal
structure. There's a person there. I
mean, if you look at this,
[Music]
um, one second, let me put this on the
screen. Here we have it.
I mean look at this. This is an
incredible structure. What is the
internal structure of this? Like what
chambers do we have inside? Do we have
any hidden chambers inside? Do we have
hidden secrets inside? There seems to be
shivaling kind of structure on the top.
Is there something be below belene the
ground? I mean there's so much to
explore right here in a chhatra. An
incredible site. It potentially is a
Mahabarat era site. Then there is
Vishali in Bihar. There is Indra Prast
in Delhi. These days it's called
Puranakila. Uh that could be the site of
ancient Indra of the Mahabharat era. In
the southern part of India we have Adi
Chelanor, Adi Chanalur in Tamil Nadu. Um
then we have places like Dwara I mean
Duara Krishna's Duara off the coast of
Gujarat. Then you have uh cave
pumatinam which is a submerged city
possibly 10,000 years old but possibly
older uh near pondicherry off the coast
of the eastern coast of India not far
from pondicherry and there is mahabali
puram there is
uh there is the ancient site of
vikramila
inj and then once again if you go south
there is uh gangai k cholapuram the
ancient imperial capital of the Chola
Empire and that is not well excavated
well well explored. So I I can give you
so many examples you know there's so
much potential for uh archaeological
studies in India so much so yeah go
ahead so study some of these sites read
up about them then once you're an
archaeologist you can go and explore
them all the
best okay Mr. 88 says why did so many
Britishers decide to stay in South
Africa after its independence and why
couldn't they repeat the same in India
we know that British interests are still
present in Africa and India through a
variety of means by how the white
population remained there not in India
or Pakistan okay the
subcontinent so uh to answer that
question first of all I will take a look
at the map I mean the map is a great
tool to understand a lot of
Um so here's the map. Now as we know
India is near the equator. India is a
pretty hot place at least large parts of
India hot. If you go to northern India
is pretty pleasant climate and all. If
you go to Ladak it's frighteningly cold
and so on. The Himalayan region is very
extreme very very cold. Uh and northern
parts of India you know Punjab Orana
Kashmir etc. Even the Nepal region even
the Arunachal region etc.
uh the u kaibar paktuna region all that
pretty good weather good climate but
most of India is hot really really hot
one of the reason why the British left
India is that they had plundered
everything they could plunder there's
nothing much left and the climate was
too hot for them they didn't enjoy it
that's why they left South Africa on the
other hand okay it's in the southern
part of Africa very very nice pleasant
weather pretty cool weather if I click
uh at the southern part of Africa The
latitude is -
34.79. - 34.79. It's it's comparable to
let's say if I go to
SI it's - 34 something. So it's it's the
same kind of weather you have at SI and
SI has good weather, good climate.
Tasmania has super cold. Uh if you go to
the northern hemisphere to give you an
example, it is like uh for example uh
what if I click here? What's the
latitude?
34 so Hiroshima so Hiroshima Coobe Kyoto
that's around the 34 degree latitude you
know it's pretty cold there right so
yeah that's the kind of weather you have
in South Africa pretty cool pretty
pretty pleasant weather so that's one
reason why the the Britishers like you
say uh were happy to stay on in South
Africa because of the climate climate
was nice it was conducing conducive for
them to stay on the second thing is that
if you look at the demographics of South
Africa the religious demographics of
South
Africa. South Africa is about 85%
Christian today. And that must have been
the case even you know uh in the 1930s
1940s. They the first thing Europeans do
is they they convert. They they destroy
the local culture. They eradicate the
local religion and they impose their
religion on the natives. That's what
they've done consistently wherever they
go. Failed in India. They tried their
best. They still they're still trying.
The Spanish did that in the Americas.
The Portuguese did that elsewhere in Goa
and so on. and the the Europeans did
they're all over Africa. So in South
Africa the native South African culture,
religion, whatever is it, whatever it
is, barely exists. About 85% of the
population is Christian. The rest is
whatever else. Right? So because of this
it was culturally also nice for the
British to stay there. People all
believed in the British um imposed
religion. In India it's very alien,
right? India, India is full of Hindus,
Hindus. So the British would not have
been very comfortable because of that as
well. So a multitude of factors multiple
factors uh would have contributed to
this. The first is the climate. Second
is the
religion and so on. So that's why
probably and and and India was
horrifically impoverished by the 1940s.
The life expectancy was what 30 31
something like
that. It's it's
like it's like being in Ethiopia of the
1970s and 80s that that sort of thing.
Horrible. India was like like a death
trap. So they had destroyed India
completely and they didn't want to stay
in such a hell hole. They had reduced
India to a hell hole essentially. So
that's why they left. South Africa was
was a very different place. Much more
pleasant for them.
So okay Pandit says Abijit Chra you
recommended virtue success pleasure and
liberation by Aliyah Danilu. I read this
book. There were certain passages that
referenced Arian invasion theory
referring to Koroas as a pandas
dravidian and termed intercast marriages
unacceptable. So you're complaining. I
referred a book and you're complaining.
This is why I don't refer that's why I
don't give any book recommendations
anymore. I have said this so many times
that there is no book that's written by
anyone about India that doesn't have any
distortions. Now Allah Danyu lived a 100
years ago. At that time everyone
believed in the arian invasion
theory. So that's why I wrote about it.
Even today there are books that are
superb but they still have distortions.
I have said this so many times. There is
no book written about India in which no
distortion exists. But there are good
aspects of the book which is why I
recommend them. But then we get people
like this who will complain who will
start nitpicking and complaining and
pointing fingers. You recommended a bad
book. So that's why I've stopped
recommending
books. I mean Indians, lot of Indians
have this habit. It's not their fault.
The education system has done it to
them. The education system it
it puts this habit in your head of
looking for tiny minute mistakes and
faults because you know in the Indian
education system your teacher in when
you write an exam paper even if you make
the smallest of mistakes they'll cut one
mark two mark whatever even if overall
you're right but because you missed a
full stop or a comma somewhere they'll
cut two marks. So Indians because of
this they are conditioned to look for
tiny minute mistakes in everything and
Indians are a nation today of
nitpickers who will simply miss the big
picture because they're all squabbbling
among each other over tiny minute things
which are completely unimportant. So
here's an example of that. I recommended
a nice book because there are some
things that are nice about the book but
the person finds problems.
So that's and I have seen this I have
have had this happen to me over and over
and over again which is why I don't
recommend books anymore. What do you
expect
anymore? Uh Phoenix says why is it so
hard for people in India to realize the
Indian system desperately needs a system
reboot? Because Indians don't get the
big picture. Because Indians are
nitpickers. Indians look for tiny minute
flaws here and there and they squabble
among each other about these tiny little
things and they completely miss the big
picture and it is not the fault of
Indians. The education system has
destroyed their ability to
think. Those who still can think are are
doing it superheroically despite the
education system, despite the trauma
imposed by the education system. But
most Indians they simply can't think.
They are mentally lovized. They can't
think. The education system has
destroyed their ability and will to
think. Thinking is
painful. So that's why Indians just
don't realize what's what's going on.
And if you say something that goes
against a prevailing narrative,
prevailing
narrative, then they will call you a
conspiracy theorist or something or you
are a conspiracy theorist or this book
said this and that or that great person
of authority said that. So how can you
go against them? H you have no idea what
you're talking about. So that's why most
Indians they will they simply engaging
in pulling each other down. When someone
tries to think against the established
narrative they'll try and pull the
person down and at the best of times
they'll Indians will be squabbbling
among each other about about tiny minute
issues. Oh Hinduism and Buddhism are
different cultures. Oh because this this
2% something is different in Buddhism
from Hinduism. So it's
different. Keep fighting over small
things and they will completely miss the
big picture. So that's the issue in
India. The root cause of the is the
education
system. Freddy Joe HS says the largest
volunteer army in the world was the
British Indian Army where 2.5 million
Indians volunteered. They saw it as much
as an Indian war as a British war.
That's why it's called the Second World
War. And I am British and I put this
thesis forth towards you silly unwashed
Indians. The largest volunteer army in
the world. This is what people in the UK
still apparently believe. H volunteers.
See in
India during the British occupation of
India, during the British during the
brutal, genocidal, barbaric British
occupation of
India, Indians were
impoverished to the nth
degree. There was no means of sustaining
yourself and of sustaining a
family unless you worked for the
oppressor. Without a government job
there was no stability, no future, no
security in
life. They had they had stolen all the
land. So nobody owned
land. In the past when people owned land
they could farm, they could do whatever
they want. And the British had also
destroyed all all of India's indigenous
industries. India was the first
ever fully industrialized
civilization. The British completely
de-industrialized India. So all the
people who had all these incredible
skills which ran in the family from
generation to generation everything was
wiped out in their entire livelihoods
were uprooted destroyed. The livelihood
that their family had had been part of
for dozens maybe hundreds of generations
was destroyed. So there is no industry
anymore. There is no agriculture
anymore. So if you want to have food on
the table for your for you and your
family, you had to work for the
government.
So then they would employ Indians as
clerks or as
soldiers. So just to stay alive, just to
provide for the family. Lots of Indians
had to become soldiers in the British
army. They didn't
volunteer. They had no
choice. You see, this was not an Indian
war. This was a European war. It was a
useless, needless
war perpetrated on the world by the
Europeans for their own petty squables.
You and your Hitler and whatnot. And you
made us fight fight fight on your
behalf. So that's what it was. Nobody
volunteered for this. The Indians who
fought had no choice. They were fighting
for their families. They were fighting
to put put food on the table. They
didn't give a damn about your your
cause. It was not our war.
And it's sad that these people who still
have these feelings of superiority, they
come up and put these comments over here
in front of
us. I mean, just take a look at the
state of the UK today. You people who
live in the UK should be ashamed of
yourselves.
Absolutely. You should be ashamed of
yourselves, of what you have allowed to
happen to your country.
Your women aren't safe in your country
today and you people aren't even able to
to to ensure their security. We know
what what the Pakistanis have been doing
to your women and you people just sat
and let this happen. You should be
ashamed of yourselves. You British
people and you have the the the g to
come here and talk talk all this and and
and say all this over here, please.
Okay. Really now says Japan and South
Korea are seem similar but are different
in many ways. Can you shed some light on
the ways they are different politically,
economically in the society? I feel it
feels like the South Koreans emulated
the West and the old Chinese culture
while Japan is a more distinct culture
despite the westernization. Also, Japan
has a much larger economy. Is it because
they weren't colonized but colonizers?
Why isn't Japanese entertainment and
music as popular but has a higher and
has a higher fertility rate? Which in
your opinion is more advanced? Okay. To
answer this, I have to do a two over
episode essentially. Okay, it's a very
complex uh topic that that you have
brought forth. Very interesting as well.
And is South Korea overhyped in front of
Japan? See, one thing they have in
common, they are both US vasals. They're
both under US occupation, permanent US
military occupation. Okay, so that
that's one thing they have in common.
Now, if you look at the geography, as
you can see, Japan is is offshore. It's
an island nation. It's an
archipelago and it's always had a
separate existence as a separate entity.
South Korea has always been under the
shadow of China for the most part to
some and also under the shadow of Japan
and Japan has always been very
independent. They of course did absorb
Chinese culture. They absorbed all of
Buddhism and Indian influence via China
which is why uh they they have a very
Chinese influence uh on their Buddhism
and on the Indian culture they've
absorbed but they are still very
different very independent very
different from South Korea and very
different from China that's Japan Japan
has a very old history uh goes back at
least two and a half thousand years
maybe more South Korea also has an
ancient history going back 2,000 or
maybe more years but they have always
been very very strongly sinized
under Chinese influence which means they
have been under Chinese influence. Uh
Japan is uh a larger nation a larger
economy and they've always
been especially since the uh major
restoration of the 19th century mid-
19th mid to late 19th century they have
been very very uh industrialized. They
have been very
uh westernized. they've tried they've
sought to emulate the west which
eventually led to their disastrous
downfall in the second world war. Um so
you could say that the major restoration
of the 19th century was the beginning of
the end of Japan because they they threw
away their old lifestyle way of life the
supremacy of the dharmic system that the
the sham samurai and shogunet system had
established and so on
um and so on. So very different cultures
very there are similarities as well
there are they have issues they have
their own issues which we'll not go into
uh at the
point politically different systems uh
economically Japan is a much bigger e
economy society the South Korean society
is is is well again different they have
taken different trajectories South Korea
has is mostly atheistic now and the rest
are Christians very few Buddhists I I
hear still remain in South Korea,
they've completely lost their indigenous
culture. When it comes to Japan, they
still retain the Shinto Buddhist
culture. Um, they also are facing
Christianization and all those problems
because of foreign occupation, but they
still have have resisted much better
than South Korea.
Um, fertility rate, both nations are
suffering very badly. South Korea's
fertility rate is catastrophically low.
Japan's is marginally better. I don't
remember the exact figures right now.
I'll not go and research it, but it's
marginally better than South Korea.
Um, so which is more advanced? Look, as
a nation, as a as a as a culture, as a
civilization, Japan is more advanced,
has always been more advanced. Uh, what
is overhyped, what is not, it depends on
the overlord. The US today both are
vasals, both are under occupation. So,
whoever the the overlord will favor will
be hyped. So they have both been given
some rewards for for being US vasals.
South Korea was allowed to industrialize
and become a major industrial power in
service of the west in service of the of
the US and it has suffered catastrophic
demographic decline as a consequence.
But they they are given a certain amount
of prestige and people are fans of K-pop
even though nobody understands the
Korean language but people for some
reason like K-pop. So that's the reward
they've been given. what are the rewards
they've been given and when it comes to
Japan they are influential in the world
through anime and and other stuff
uh video games all of that and so on
overall I would say Japan is u from my
perspective at least is a is is a more
significant culture and civilization uh
than Korea that's the way I see
it right let's take a couple more
questions and I'll take questions from
the live chat. Maybe there's not enough
time. I'll just go for the live chat
now. How about that? We'll do live chat
for about 10 15
minutes.
Um, Matthew Perez says, "UK is warped.
Glad I live in Texas. We got Texas
justice." Okay, Texas justice. I think
it's it's not a bad idea. Texas justice.
What else the Okay, let's see the some
of the uh questions from the live
chat. My views on the movie Animal. I
haven't watched the movie Animal, so I
can't say. Vak board. Yeah. Yeah.
Something has happened. Look, I don't
comment on internal politics, internal
matters mostly. And I haven't even
studied what's happened. Okay. I know
the Vak Act has been passed, but I have
not studied it. I look at geopolitics. I
look at the big picture. There are other
picture who look other people who look
at the internal picture. We all are on
the same team but we we we we serve
different functions. So I I I have not
really looked into the VA waka board
matter.
Um which IPL team do I support? I don't
watch IPL. I watched the first season of
the IPL which which was what 2007 2008.
The Pakistanis were still playing at the
time. The first season the Pakistanis
played and the first match Brendan
McCullum hit 158 or something. The last
match was Shane W's last professional
match I believe and he was on the
non-strikers end when Sahel Talir hit
the winning runs for Rajasthan Royals
for yeah that one. So I watched the
first season after that I lost
interest. I think it's very artificial.
I think it's very made up. Every two
three years the teams are re reshuffled.
So there's no continuity.
Sometimes one team disappears like CSK
disappears for two three years. Then
there is some super giant team that
comes and disappears again. There's no
continuity and I mean these are all six
hitting
fests. The bowler has no role in this to
a very large extent. I like to see
balance between bat and
ball. I like to see the batsman being
made to respect the bowler but in the IP
result it's all just hit sixes. hit
everything for six. I just don't find it
interesting. I I like sports. I I enjoy
all sports. I've played some sports as
well. Uh when it comes to cricket, I
like test match cricket. I even like T20
one day. It should be international, not
this. This is just a merrygoround. So I
I don't watch IPL. I don't enjoy it. I I
don't mean to offend any of you who
watch IPL. Please enjoy IPL. Please
please watch whatever you like. It's
entirely your choice. This is merely my
perspective.
But I' I've seen cricket for a very long
time and it's no longer the same these
days.
Um Shri Ramachandra says, "What's your
favorite food?" These days I eat one
meal a day. I'm trying to get a little
fitter, meaner, leaner.
Um so I eat one source of protein and a
large quantity of vegetables. Then I eat
and I eat a large bunch a large quantity
of watermelon as well. It's the simple
foods that are fun. So that's what I
look I like food. I like all kinds of
food. I like foods. Foods. I like every
cuisine. I like most cuisines. Japanese,
uh,
Mexican, uh, French cuisine, Thai
cuisine, Indian cuisine, obviously we
like it. Chinese, Mongolian,
um, Eastern African cuisine is very
interesting. It's similar to Indian
cuisine. Arabic cuisine, it's nice. You
know, the if you if you look at Arabic
cuisine, there's so many good vegetarian
dishes you get over there. You know, the
mezz platters, the the the stuffed wine
leaves, wine is grape wine leaves
stuffed with rice and whatnot. There is
muham. It's a very nice thing. There's
so many nice cuisines in the world.
Croatian cuisine is nice. You may even
say a few good things about British
cuisine.
Russian cuisine is nice. Hungarian
cuisine. I I like all foods. Look, I
don't have one favorite food. Anything
that's cooked well, you know, with with
passion and love, it's going to taste
good. So, yeah, my my approach to
cuisine is like my approach to music. I
like it all. I enjoy it
all.
Okay. I was looking at something else
and this comes up. Okay. Ritik says if a
young individual between the age of 20
25 with no political background aspires
to be a leader of this country one day
what paths are available to them only
democratic or coup or through
AI the current system will not allow any
coups you will have to go do it through
the democratic way you'll have to enter
some political party show that you are
capable of being a leader which means
you know what is the measure of a leader
at the grassroots level to prove
yourself you have to show how many
people you can thing on the street on
demand. That's the value of your
leadership. So a so that's why lots of
leaders in India in Indian politics
emerge from from colleges and
universities student politics because
they have a readym made pool of students
at their at their disposal and if you if
they have the leadership qualities the
political leadership qualities they'll
be able to mobilize students and bring
them on the streets on demand. So then
when you can do that over and over again
the political party will see this guy
has potential. So then you will be
fasttracked based on your performance
and then you'll have to perform in other
ways and you to become part of the
system and see all the good and bad
parts of it and so on. That's how it
goes. AI won't work in India at this
point in time. At this point in time no
chance for AI to work coup. Haha. I mean
come on. Are you kidding yourself? How
old are
you? I think you still have a little bit
of growing up to do. If you want to
learn how to do a coup, read the book
Kuda, a practical handbook by Edward
Lutwak, who has appeared on my podcast.
It's a very interesting book. And it is
said that after a failed coup attempt in
Africa, I don't remember which country
it was, but the person who attempted the
coup, his body was found with gunshot
wounds. And inside his jacket was that
book by Edward Lutwak, Kuda, practical
handbook. It's actually a pretty good
book if you want to learn how the
mechanics and dynamics of a coup are. Uh
yeah, but I would not recommend trying a
coup in India. It is of course illegal.
It is not in the country's interests.
I'm just being a little light-hearted
here. If you want to look at a coup from
a theoretical perspective, but the only
path available to you in the current
system is to do it the hard way, bottom
up. Or you could be a very rich person
and buy your way into a political party.
There there's multiple ways. But if you
are a young kid, 20 25 years old, the
only way is to uh do it through student
politics. Show that you are a great
student leader who can mobilize people
students on the streets on demand. On
demand essentially then you will have a
great future. That's how it goes. That's
how it
goes. Abijit Chow Light says any update
about aliens and UFOs. I have not been
paying attention to aliens and UFOs.
Right now, they are not they're not
anymore the flavor of the season. Aliens
and UFOs. A few months ago, they were
UFOs were all over the place in New
Jersey and in the US. I mean, there was
an invasion of UFOs on live TV. They
were showing UFOs flying over the sky.
Now, they've all disappeared.
And then after Trump comes to power, his
uh spokesperson, that lady, I forget her
name, whatever it is, the press
secretary, she said that those UFOs or
whatever were
drones and and they were being they they
were being deployed by the Biden Biden
administration. So they were not really
alien artifacts. They were drones,
advanced
drones belonging to the United States
government. Now if you look at those
videos which is very interesting some of
those drones they morph they they
change from aircraft or drone like
structures
to to orbs which is very strange very
interesting but
yeah Navin Kumar says GoGa or Bangkok
I've never been to Goa so I can't say
I've been to Bangkok once hardly saw the
place I went for the World Hindu
Congress in the end of 2023. I found
Bangkok fascinating. Very beautiful
place, a very nice people. What I loved
about Bangkok is that nobody bothers to
speak English. They all speak Thai. But
you can somehow communicate, you know,
and they are more Indian than us. They
are more Dharmic than us. Okay, they and
it is their culture. It's not our
culture anymore. It's their culture they
are practicing and they value their
culture. If you go if you go to those
airport Bangkok so nabi you will
see manifestations of of dharmic um
dharmic manifestations everywhere
whether it is hanuman whether it is the
samudraan whatever all Indian cultural
elements portrayed there as Thai
elements and they're proud of it they're
not ashamed of it so different from
India so I would so I have never been to
Goa so I can't say anything about Goa
but I really like Bangkok the brief time
I was there like 3 days or something. It
was fun. I don't mind going again.
Wonderful place and I would like to
explore more of Thailand and more of
Southeast
Asia.
Um Rajil Kh thank you so much for
becoming a member. I never ask anybody
to become a member but some of you still
do that. So I really appreciate that.
Thank you so much to everybody who has
purchased memberships despite me never
asking anyone to do that. Thank you so
much and thank you so much Rajil. I
really appreciate it. Thank you for your
support. It means a
lot. Okay, let's
um I have spoken about Okay, let's see
this. Uh Rajil says, "Can you please
explain about private data security and
theft?" Sun alien private data security
and theft. That's a very technical
subject. It's a very corporate subject,
isn't it? So, look, every corporation,
every entity, every individual has some
private data, right? We all have it. uh
you may have a laptop in which you have
your own private data whatever word
documents or uh whatever it is that you
keep PDFs or videos or whatever that's
your private data. Okay. Um and that
needs to be
secure and it can be stolen as well. So
maybe you have credit card information
or maybe you have some financial
statements or maybe you have passwords
or something. If it is stolen then it
becomes a huge problem for you. People
can steal your money, people can steal
your identity or whatever. So you need
to keep it secure and there are multiple
ways of doing it. You can encrypt your
data so that nobody can you know crack
it. Crack the code. That's one way of
doing it. Private security, private data
security. Another way is to disconnect
your laptop your your your machine
whatever it is from the internet is
called air gapping. An airgapped system
which is secure because no internet can
penetrate there. If you want to be
really airgapped then you can have a
room with um what's called a faradic
cage. In case you don't know what a
faradic cage is, look at a microwave
oven. If you look at the front window of
the microwave oven, you can see a grill
structure over it. Grill. That's a
Faraday cage which keeps the microwaves
inside and prevents them from leaking
out of the microwave oven. So you can
have a room with a faradic cage situ
paradise kind of a kind of setup which
will genuinely ensure that no outside
signal comes in or no inside signal goes
out. So there are various ways of
achieving proper data security.
Most of us we have systems that are
connected to the internet. So you have
to u ensure that you don't keep any
sensitive information first of all on um
your internet connected
system. Um and if you have such
information you need to keep it secure
in a variety of ways. Yeah. And theft
there's there are lots of ways of of of
stealing
uh private data. You know hackers this
they specialize in this and some hackers
are really good. There are various ways
of doing it. The Chinese are good at it.
Apparently India is not not bad in in
cyber security. One hears one hears
whispers. Okay. So yeah there are people
who are professionals and who can do
that. So you've got to uh you got to
employ basic common sense essentially.
So that's what I can say. It's a very
very big topic very complex topic. You
can do like one single twoour live
stream only about this but that's what
I'll say in brief about
this. All right. Um um
um Mr. Adus says do I listen to
electronic or Indian music? Electronic
music some of it was used to be good.
There was this
uh this band called Astral Projection.
They had this song called Mahadeva.
There was nice electronic music. Some of
it is good. Some of it is good. Um, I
don't really keep up with electronic
music these days. Ambient music used to
be good. Ambient music should be
something that allows you to focus on
the work that you're doing, but it
should create a nice ambiance, nice
atmosphere. Ambient music is is
something I'm still into sometimes. So,
yeah, I do I do listen to it
sometimes. And
um Okay.
Um, what shall I do? What shall I do?
What shall I shall I take one more?
Who's my favorite sports person says
Mayori? I don't know. I don't have any
one favorite sports person. I I've
admired lots of sports people from
different sports. Uh for example in
tennis
I what uh Roger Federer Noak Jookovic I
used to like Agassi uh Pete Sampras
uh among women Stephy Graph Monica Chesh
these days I have no idea who uh maybe
the the Williams Serena Williams
probably who else in in cricket there
are so many Viv Richards
uh Jeff Thompson if anyone remembers him
and so on so any I mean there's no one
person that's my favorite. Okay, with
that we will end today's live stream. We
are way past 2 hours. So thank you so
much for all the questions. I enjoyed
this very much. Enjoyed the questions I
took from the comments. Enjoy the
questions I took from the live chat and
we shall keep doing this and the next
episode will be next week. Same time,
same channel, same day. So until then
take care. Thank you so much for
everything. Thank you so much for your
viewership. Please keep asking
questions. Please keep raising your
standards. Please keep learning.
Take care. I'll see you soon. Bye-bye.